<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Full and true relation of a most barbarous and dreadful murder committed on the body of Mrs. Kirk, wife of Edmund Kirk, drawer at the Rose-Tavern in Pye-Corner, on Sunday, May the 25th, 1684, whose body was found in a pit near Tyburn, supposed to be murder'd by her aforesaid husband</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2315C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11370</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13791494</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13791494</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101849</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40586)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101849)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 454:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Full and true relation of a most barbarous and dreadful murder committed on the body of Mrs. Kirk, wife of Edmund Kirk, drawer at the Rose-Tavern in Pye-Corner, on Sunday, May the 25th, 1684, whose body was found in a pit near Tyburn, supposed to be murder'd by her aforesaid husband</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Elizabeth Mallet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kirk, --  Mrs., d. 1684.</term>
               <term>Kirk, Edmund, d. 1684.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101849:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101849:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A full and true RELATION OF a moſt Barbarous and Dreadful MURDER; Committed on the Body of Mrs. <hi>Kirk,</hi> wife of Edmund Kirk Drawer at the <hi>Roſe-Tavern</hi> in PYE-CORNER, On <hi>Sunday May</hi> the 25th. 1684.</head>
            <head type="sub">Whoſe Body was found in a Pit near <hi>Tyburn,</hi> ſuppoſed to be Murder'd by her aforeſaid Husband.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>EDmund Kirk</hi> was a <hi>Drawer</hi> at the <hi>Roſe-Tavern</hi> at <hi>Pye-Corner,</hi> where he had liv'd with the Maſter of the Houſe about a Fortnight or three Weeks at moſt; <hi>Friday</hi> the 23 <hi>d.</hi> of this Inſtant, being the day of the Execution of <hi>John Gower</hi> who Mutthered his Wife, and <hi>Francis Robinſon,</hi> who were then Executed at <hi>Tyburn;</hi> he aſked his Maſters leave that he might go and ſee them ſuffer, and at his return, brought back the Speeches and Confeſſions of them, which he particularly related to the Family. Much about the time he came to his aforeſaid Maſter, he was Married to a Woman who was Servant in a Lawyers houſe in <hi>Dove Court</hi> on <hi>Fiſh-ſtreet Hill,</hi> and on Sunday in the Afternoon went to ſee his ſaid Wife, and invited her to walk into the Fields, as appears by the other Servants: they took their walk towards <hi>Paddington,</hi> and about ſeven a Clock at Night <hi>Edmund Kirk</hi> returned to his Maſters Houſe, where he was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be in a great heat, but not any ways Melancholy, or Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in his Temper.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Tueſday</hi> Morning, about ten of the Clock the Body of a Woman Murdered, was found in a Pit within two Fields of <hi>Tyburn,</hi> her Arms and other parts of her Body were black and blew, and her
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101849:2"/> Throat c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t from one Ear to another. The Conſtable of <hi>Paddington</hi> acquainted with it, came to view the Body, and ſearching the Pockets of this poor murder'd Wretch, found a Letter which ſhe deſigned to ſend to ſome Friends in the Country, and was writ by her Maſters Clark, vvith Directions in it hovv to ſend to her. By the Directions of the Letter, he acquainted her Maſter, that the Body of a vvoman was found Murder'd at ſuch a place, and ſuch a Letter in her Pocket. The Gentleman having miſt his Servant from <hi>Sunday,</hi> and knovving that her Husband liv'd vvith a Vintner at the <hi>Roſe-Tavern</hi> at <hi>Pye-Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> vvent this Morning, being the 28th of <hi>May,</hi> to his Maſters Houſe, vvhere examining him about his Wife, he ſeemed in a ſtrange horror and confuſion of Spirit, upon vvhich he vvas carried before Sr. <hi>William Turner,</hi> vvho Committed him to <hi>Nengate.</hi> He did ovvn before Sr. <hi>William,</hi> that he vvent out with her tovvards <hi>Paddington,</hi> and vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſaid he brought her back again; but the Circumſtances appearing very plain againſt him, he confeſſed he vvalked vvith her from her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Houſe tovvards <hi>Paddington,</hi> and at three of the Clock in the Afternoon, he vvent from his Maſters Houſe to his Wife, and vvithout his Maſters Knovvledge took his Cane from behind the door, and at his return at ſeven a Clock, brought it back vvith him and ſet it in the ſame place. When the Body vvas found, there vvas alſo found a Braſs Ferule of a Cane, of vvhich notice being given to Sr. <hi>Wm. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> the Cane vvas produced, vvhich vvas bloody a foot from the end of it, &amp; the Ferule off; vvhich ſaid Ferule by the Deſcription the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of <hi>Paddington</hi> has given of it, does certainly belong to the ſaid <hi>Cane. Edmund Kirk,</hi> does acknowledge that he took the ſaid Cane out with him but will not plainly and poſitively confeſs the Murder, <hi>tho</hi> by all Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, he does appear to be the cruel and barbarous Author of it. He continued at his Maſters houſe at <hi>Pye-Corner</hi> from the time of the commtting of this Murder, and did not in his carriage and behavior appear to his Maſter or Fellow Servants under any trouble or diſquiet of mind, till this very morning, vvhen he vvas apprehended; and then vvas under a ſtrange ſurprize and conſternation, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled <hi>like</hi> an <hi>Aſpin-Leafe.</hi> The poor Woman vvho vvas thus inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Butcher'd, vvas judg'd by thoſe vvho <hi>knew</hi> her before this fatal miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and by others vvho have ſeen the body ſince, to have been vvith Child, vvhich probably ſhe vvas before Marriage: and ſome little Items have been <hi>taken</hi> notice of in his former Expreſſions, as if his marriage had been rather upon force, to prevent a greater ſhame than in the choice of his Affections; vvhat vvas the true cauſe, does not yet plainly appear, but he vvas obſerved to diſcourſe unvvillingly of her &amp; vvas alvvays diſpleaſed vvith any expreſſions vvhich related to her.</p>
            <p>Thus by this lamentable inſtance may wee ſee the ſtrange power the Devil has over the mind and affections of ſome men, who as this perſon, tho he had ſeen <hi>John Gower</hi> Executed on the Fryday before for murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Wife, yet could <hi>take</hi> no warning from his ſad example, but on Sunday following (a day which more particularly ought to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred him from ſo Bloody a murder) commits the ſame crime himſelf, by which <hi>he</hi> may expect <hi>the ſame</hi> miſerable and <hi>ſhameful death.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London Printed by <hi>Elizabeth Mallet</hi> in <hi>Black-Horſe Alley</hi> near <hi>Fleet-Bridge,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
